Guide to the Barbara S. Buckley Papers, 1941-1959
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Barbara S. Buckley Papers
1941-1959
Buckley, Barbara S.
6 boxes (2 cubic feet)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Collection consists primarily of musical compositions, both original manuscripts and copy prints, as well as a small volume of correspondence, press clippings, writings and biographical documentation.
Biographical Note
Barbara S. Buckley (Mallinckrodt) was born in Wilmington, Delaware and was both a musician (piano, violin and flute) and composer. She studied at the American School at Fontainebleau under the direction of Nadia Boulanger. Buckley also studied at Boston University, Vassar College (Class of 1945), and Bryn Mawr (1941). Her compositions include a symphony, string quartets, chamber music for strings and piano, solo piano works, a work for solo organ, songs, sacred choral music, and chamber music for winds or brass.
Scope and Content Note
The Barbara S. Buckley Papers, 1941 - 1959, contain Buckley’s musical compositions, both original manuscripts and photostat copies. Files include her notations and sketches for works created between 1948 and 1959. One letter sized document box contains four folders of correspondence, one of which includes a note from Buckley’s mentor, Nadia Boulanger. Files include press clippings, programs, and two folders of writings by Buckley, possibly from her work as an undergraduate student. One reference folder contains inventory lists describing the collection’s contents, one created at the time of the collection’s accession to Vassar College (including lyrics of selected pieces), and one handwritten collection of inventory lists, circa 1950s.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Boulanger, Nadia; Golschmann, Vladimir, 1893-1972
Organizations:
Subjects:
Violin and viola music--Scores; Organ and piano music--Scores; Vocal music--Scores
VCL Categories
Music
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, 2019.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Elizabeth Bryden, 2017.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into seven series. Compositions are arranged alphabetically, as titled by the creator.
Series List
- Series I. Compositions, 1948-1959; (Boxes 1-5)
  - Orchestral Works, 1952-1959; (Boxes 1-2)
  - Piano and Organ Works, 1951-1959; (Box 2)
  - Quartets, 1950-1959; (Boxes 2-3)
  - Small Ensembles, 1950-1959; (Boxes 3-4)
  - Violin and Viola, 1953-1958; (Box 4)
  - Vocal Works, 1948-1959; (Box 5)
- Series II. Biographical, 1943-1959; (Box 6)
- Series III. Correspondence, 1949-1958; (Box 6)
- Series IV. Press Clippings, 1947; (Box 6)
- Series V. Programs and Invitations, 1953-1958; (Box 6)
- Series VI. Writings, 1941-1942; (Box 6)
- Series VII. Reference, undated; (Box 6)
Container List
- Series I. Compositions
  - Orchestral Works
    - Divertimento for String Orchestra no. 1, full score and parts, negative print, original MS and bound copy, 1954-1955 (1.1)
    - Overture to Winterset, original MS (1.2)
    - Passacaglia for Orchestra (Carlo Gesualdo), original MS, 1959 (1.3)
    - Symphony no. 1, original MS, negative copy, 1952-1954; (2 bound copies) (1.4 - 1.6, 2.1)
    - Symphony no. 2 in D, One Movement, original MS, draft (2.2)
  - Piano and Organ Works
    - Sonata no. 1 in D, “For Mrs. Olga Muller and Eudoxia Woodward,” original MS and print, 1955 (2.3)
    - Sonatine Pour Deux Pianos, (3) original MSS, 1954 (2.4)
    - Arietta for Organ, (2) prints, 1951 (2.5)
    - Pianoforte, Variations on a theme by Paganini, original MS, unfinished, 1959 (2.6)
    - Sonata Pour Piano, (3) MSS, 1954 (2.7)
  - Quartets
    - Children’s Quartet, Five Pieces for Children, original MSS, 1950-1953 (2.8 - 2.10)
    - Hidden Words, String Quartet, Prière de Salut, Commune of Healing, Soprano solo, original MS, prints and parts, including sketches, 1959 (3.1)
    - String Quartet no. 1, master score and parts, 1957 (3.2)
    - String Quartet no. 2, original MS and parts (copies), 1959 (3.3)
  - Small Ensembles
    - Concert no. 1 (Kleine), violins I and II, viola II - Ubellaunig, 1951 (3.4)
    - Concerto for Two Trumpets and String Orchestra, includes unfinished sketches, 1959 (3.5)
    - Oboe Trio, Sonate Pour Oboe, Cello, Piano, original MS and parts, notes and copies, 1958-1959 (3.6)
    - Oboe Trio, original MS and parts, 1959 (3.7)
    - Quintetta I, violin, (2) photocopied MSS, 1950-1953 (3.8)
    - Quintetta I, strings and piano score (parts), photocopied MS, 1950-1953 (3.9)
    - Sonata for oboe, violoncello and piano, original MS and photocopies (4.1)
    - Suite for Percussion and Piano, original MS and parts, 1958-1959 (4.2)
    - Trio for Strings, Op. 2, original MS and parts (4.3)
    - Woodwind Quintet, original MS, unfinished, 1954 (4.4)
  - Violin and Viola
    - Petite Suite for Two Violins, original MS, 1953 (4.5)
    - Sonata no. 1 for Viola and Piano, original MS, 1958 (4.6)
    - Sonata no. 2 in D, violin and piano, “To L. Voserchian and E. Dick,” original MS, negative and positive prints, 1954 (4.7)
    - Sonata for Violin and Piano, “To Mr. and Mrs. Alfred Krips,” MS score, master sheets, (1) bound copy (4.8)
  - Vocal Works
    - A Voice on the Winds (Lionel Johnson), soprano, piano, master copy, 1951 (5.1)
    - Air for Contralto and Viola, St. John 14:27, master print, 1951 (5.2)
    - Canata no. 1 (By Night On My Bed I Sought Him), soprano, cello, piano, original MSS, master copies, 1958 (5.3)
    - Communion Service, Children’s Choir, Organ, Viola, All Saints Episcopal Church, (2) original MSS, 1955 (5.4)
    - Comparative Analysis, soprano, piano, original MS, 1957 (5.5)
    - Love Song, Op. 3, no. 1 (Robert Nichols), voice, piano, original MSS, positive and negative prints, 1948 (5.6)
    - Lullaby for Christopher (Sapp), soprano, piano, original MSS, 1952 (5.7)
    - Missa Brevis, choir, 2 violins, 2 flutes, drum triange, 2 trumpets in B flat, original MS, photocopies, 1954-1959 (5.8)
    - The Navigators, Op. 3, no. 3 (Walter James Turner), baritone, piano, original MS, negative and positive prints, 1949 (5.9)
    - Pie Jesu, soprano, piano, photocopy, 1951 (5.10)
    - Psalm 1 Op. 4, no. 1, psalm 1:1-3 King James Version, soprano, alto, tenor, bass chorus, piano, original MS, negative and positive prints, 1949 (5.11)
    - Psalm 139, contralto, piano, original MS, mock up, master and copies (5.12)
    - The Snail (John Donne), tenor, baritone, piano, original MS, 1957 (5.13)
    - Spirit, Silken Thread (Margo Ruddock), medium voice, piano, master copies, 1952 (5.14)
    - To Quick My Ear (Emily Dickinson), voice, piano, original MS, incomplete, 1957 (5.15)
    - A Widow Bird, Op. 3, no. 3 (Walter James Turner), baritone, piano, original MS, positive and negative prints, 1949 (5.16)
    - Winter Song (Oliver Heford), voice, piano, MS draft, 1952 (5.17)
- Series II. Biographical
  - Certificate of Attendance, Ecoles des Americaines, 1952 (6.1)
  - Handwritten text and notations addressing congressional bill regarding scientific research and study, 1945-09-28 (6.2)
  - School transcript, Boston University School of Fine and Applied Arts, 1959 (6.3)
  - Vassar College, Italian assignments, 1943-02-17 (6.4)
  - Vassar College report card, 1943 February (6.5)
- Series III. Correspondence (to BSB)
  - Boulanger, Nadia, 1957-09-16 (6.6)
  - Compton, Arthur H. (telegram), 1949 (6.7)
  - Golschmann, Vladimir, (2) letters, 1957 (6.8)
  - Rudolf, Max, Cincinnati Symphony Orchestra, 1958-11-29 (6.9)
- Series IV. Press clippings
  - (4) clippings, 1947, undated (6.10)
- Series V. Programs and invitations
  - Isabella Stewart Gardner Museum, Mademoiselle Nadia Boulanger Reception, 1958-04-24 (6.11)
  - St. Louis Women’s Symphony, Palais de Fountainebleu, 1947, 1953 (6.12)
- Series VI. Writings
  - A Small Anthology, TS, 1942-05-12 (6.13)
  - Essays, holograph, 1941 (6.14)
- Series VII. Reference
  - Composition inventory lists, including lyrics of selected works (6.15)